Indiana University Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures records, 1949-2004 C376
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures records
1949-2004
1950-1970
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures
C376
11 cubic feet 11 boxes
Formerly part of the Department of Slavic Studies, the Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures was established as an independent department in 1958. Fields of study in the department include concentrations on the languages, literature, and linguistics of the Slavic and non-Slavic East European peoples. Included in this collection are administrative files, faculty and teaching personnel files, and materials on the language programs and workshops sponsored by the department.
Access Restrictions
Files in the Faculty and teaching personnel series still hold a large number of recommendations and social security numbers and are currently closed. Researchers must notify archives staff well in advance if they would like to see these files so that there is time to review and pull confidential material.
Advance notice required for access to collection.
Administrative History
Although Russian had been taught in previous years as part of the war effort, in the fall of 1947, Michael Ginsburg began his tenure at IU as professor of Russian language and literature. Within two years, the need and desire for study in this area grew and in 1949, the Board of Trustees approved the establishment of the Department of Slavic Studies, with Prof. Ginsburg serving as its first chair. In 1958, the department was reorganized and renamed. The Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures concentrated on the languages, literatures, and linguistics of the Slavic and non-Slavic East European peoples, while the Russian and East European Institute, absorbing the already-in-place Institute of East European Studies, focused on the area subjects.
The Dept. of Slavic Languages and Literatures provides a course of study in the language, literature, culture and linguistics of Russia, Bosnia/Croatia/Serbia, Czechoslovakia, Poland, Romania and Ukraine. In addition to offering bachelor and master degrees, IU is the only university in the state of Indiana to offer a Ph.D. in Slavic Languages and Literature.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into four series: Programs and workshops; Administrative files; Teaching files; and Faculty and teaching personnel.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Indiana University Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures is organized into four series: Programs and workshops; Administrative files; Teaching files; and Faculty and teaching personnel.
The first series, Programs and workshops, is arranged alphabetically by folder title and contains a wide variety of material relating to the various programs and workshops organized by the department. Included in this series is a significant number of records relating to the department's work with the National Defense Education Act (NDEA) and includes proposals, reports, publicity materials, and administrative files for programs supported by NDEA. Also included are materials for intensive Russian and Slavic workshops and language study tours arranged by the department.
Administrative files, the second series, is arranged alphabetically by folder heading and includes correspondence, enrollment statistics, and materials relating to Indiana Slavic Studies, a journal edited by members of the department.
The third series, Teaching files, is a small series arranged alphabetically by course number and consists of syllabi and course descriptions for a small number of courses provided by the department.
The final series, Faculty and teaching personnel, consists of a wide variety of materials relating to specific faculty and teaching personnel including language instructors and lecturers. Included in this series are correspondence, publications, and recommendations. These files still hold a large number of recommendations and social security numbers and are currently closed. Researchers must notify archives staff well in advance if they would like to see these files so that there is time to review and pull confidential material.
Separated Material
Upon review, the transfers from Slavic Languages and Literatures held quite a bit more than just departmental files. Personal files belonging to William B. Edgerton were removed from this collection and can be found in C375. Administrative materials for the Inter-University Committee on Travel Grants were removed from this collection and can be found in C379. Teaching manuals belonging to Anna Borovkoff can be found in C380, and the papers of Samuel Fiszman are located in C381.
Approximately 400 photographs and negatives have been transferred to the photograph collection. The photographs consist of images from the NDEA programs that took place on IU's campus and the Russian and Slavic Workshops.
Acquisition Information
Accession Information: 2001/055, 2008/087, 5042-5044
Provenance
Transferred from the Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures to the University Archives, July 2001, October 2008, and August 1980.
Slavic languages. Study and teaching (Higher) --Indiana --Bloomington.; Slavic literature. Study and teaching (Higher) --Indiana --Bloomington.; Indiana University. Department of Slavic Studies -- Archives; Indiana University. Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures -- History -- Sources; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures -- History -- Sources; Indiana University. Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures -- Archives; Indiana University. Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. Department of Slavic Studies -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. Department of Slavic Studies -- History -- Sources
- Programs and Workshops, 1951-1976 (Box 1)
  - National Defense Education Act (NDEA) (Box 1)
    - Act, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Budget, 1962-1968 (Box 1)
    - Conference, Columbus, Ohio, 1971; undated (Box 1)
    - Contracts (Box 1)
      - 1959‑1960 (Box 1)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 1)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 1)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
      - Summer 1966 (Box 1)
      - Summer 1967 (Box 1)
      - Summer 1968 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence on Fellowships, 1959-1966 (Box 1)
    - Director's Meeting, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Evaluation of Institutes, 1960-1966 (Box 1)
    - Handbook, Directors, 1964-1969 (Box 1)
    - Historical File, 1958-1965 (Box 1)
    - Housing Academic Year Institutes, 1962-1966 (Box 1)
    - Inquiries for future Mailing Lists, Academic Year, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Language Development Section, General Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Lecturers Academic Year, 1962-1966 (Box 1)
    - Manual Proposal Preparation Information, 1964-1969 (Box 1)
    - Minnesota Mining and MFG. Co., 1968 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, Summer (Box 1)
      - 1961 (Box 1)
      - 1962 (Box 1)
      - 1963 (Box 1)
      - 1964 (Box 1)
    - MLA (Modern Language Association) Scores, 1961-1966 (Box 1)
    - National Association of Secondary School Principals, 1962 (Box 1)
    - NDEA Institute (Box 1)
      - 1965 (Box 1)
      - 1966 (Box 1)
      - 1967 (Box 1)
      - 1968 (Box 1)
    - National Education Improvement Act, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Orientation Information (Academic Year), 1958-1965 (Box 1)
    - Other Institutes, Official Lists, 1961-1968 (Box 1)
    - Plan of Operation (Box 1)
      - 1960‑1961 (Box 1)
      - Summer 1961 (Box 1)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 1)
      - Summer 1963 (Box 1)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
      - Summer 1964 (Box 1)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
      - Summer 1965 (Box 1)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
      - Summer 1966 (Box 1)
  - National Defense Education Act (Box 2)
    - Plan of Operation (Box 2)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1967 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1968 (Box 2)
    - Post Doctoral Foreign Language Programs Conference, 1960 (Box 2)
    - Programs, Etc., 1962-1965 (Box 2)
    - Proposals (Box 2)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 2)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 2)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1962 (Box 2)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1963 (Box 2)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1964 (Box 2)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1965 (Box 2)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1966 (Box 2)
      - Summer, Undergraduate, 1966 (Box 2)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1967 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1968 (Box 2)
    - Publicity (Box 2)
      - Summer 1959 (Box 2)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 2)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1961 (Box 2)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1962 (Box 2)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1963 (Box 2)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1964 (Box 2)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1965 (Box 2)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1966 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1967 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1968 (Box 2)
    - Reports (Box 2)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 2)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1961 (Box 2)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1962 (Box 2)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1963 (Box 2)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1964 (Box 2)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1965 (Box 2)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1966 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1967 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1968 (Box 2)
    - Roster (Box 2)
      - Cumulative, 1959-1966 (Box 2)
      - Students, 1959-1967 (Box 2)
    - Schedules (Box 2)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 2)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 2)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 2)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - Slavic Languages and Cultures (Box 2)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 2)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 2)
      - Summer 1961 (Box 2)
  - National Defense Education Act (Box 3)
    - Slavic Languages and Cultures (Box 3)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 3)
      - Summer 1962 (Box 3)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 3)
      - Summer 1963 (Box 3)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 3)
      - Summer 1964 (Box 3)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 3)
      - Summer 1965 (Box 3)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 3)
      - Summer 1966 (Box 3)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Summer 1967 (Box 3)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 3)
      - Summer 1968 (Box 3)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 3)
      - Summer 1969 (Box 3)
      - 1969-1970 (Box 3)
      - Summer 1970 (Box 3)
      - 1970-1971 (Box 3)
      - Summer 1971 (Box 3)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 3)
      - Summer 1971 (Box 3)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      - Summer 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      - Proposal Working Papers, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - Staff, 1962-1965 (Box 3)
  - National Defense Education Act (Box 4)
    - Statistics (Box 4)
      - Academic, 1969-1971 (Box 4)
      - Summer, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Ideas and Suggestions for Future Workshops, 1965-1969 (Box 4)
  - Russian Workshop (Box 4)
    - 1951 (Box 4)
    - 1952 (Box 4)
    - 1953 (Box 4)
    - 1954 (Box 4)
    - 1955 (Box 4)
    - 1956 (Box 4)
    - 1957 (Box 4)
    - 1958 (Box 4)
    - 1959 (Box 4)
  - Slavic Workshop (Box 4)
    - 1960 (Box 4)
    - 1961 (Box 4)
    - 1962 (Box 4)
    - 1963 (Box 4)
    - 1964 (Box 4)
    - 1965 (Box 4)
    - 1966 (Box 4)
    - 1967 (Box 4)
    - 1968 (Box 4)
    - 1969 (Box 4)
    - 1970 (Box 4)
    - 1971 (Box 4)
    - 1972 (Box 4)
    - 1974 (Box 4)
    - Chronological File, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Final Report, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Workshop Materials (Dan Armstrong), 1975 (Box 4)
  - Tours (Box 4)
    - Bulgarian Tour, 1969-1974 (Box 4)
    - Polish, 1966-1968 (Box 4)
    - Russia, 1962-1969 (Box 4)
    - Serbo-Croatian (Box 4)
      - 1969-1971 (Box 4)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 4)
- Administrative, 1949-1990; undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 4)
    - 1961-1965 (Box 4)
    - 1966-1974 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - 1976-1981 (Box 5)
    - January-August 1985 (Box 5)
    - Armstrong, Daniel, 1975-1978 (Box 5)
    - Feldstein, R., August 1985-November 1988 (Box 5)
    - Soudakoff, Stephen, 1975-1981 (Box 5)
  - Department (Box 5)
    - Meetings, 1974-1982 (Box 5)
    - Memos and Other Businessundated, 1981-1983 (Box 5)
  - Departmental Publicity (Box 5)
    - 1949-1962 (Box 5)
    - undated, 1960-1981; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Enrollments (Box 5)
    - 1949-1971 (Box 5)
    - 1949-1984 (Box 5)
    - 1972-1982 (Box 5)
  - Indiana Slavic Studies (Box 5)
    - Material for Volumes III, IV, and V, 1963-1974; (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Volumes II, IV, and Vundated, 1965-1975 (Box 5)
  - Indiana Slavic Studies, Volume 5, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Slavic Workshop, Past Budget Information, 1966-1975; (4 folders) (Box 6)
- Teaching files, 1966-1987; undated (Box 6)
  - B521: Russian Literary Criticism, 1966-1969 (Box 6)
  - R563-564: Russian Literature in its European Context, 1978-1987; undated (Box 6)
  - S149: Polish Film Culture, undated (Box 6)
  - S149: Special Topics: Introduction to Modern Russian Literature, undated (Box 6)
  - S528: Seminar in Slavic Literature, 1971; undated (Box 6)
  - S566: Pro-Seminar in Literature, 1967-1986 (Box 6)
  - S583: Advanced Structure of Russian: Lexicology, 1970 (Box 6)
  - S583: Advanced Structure of Russian: Morphology, 1970 (Box 6)
- Faculty and teaching personnel, 1949-2004; undated (Box 6)
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is closed to researchers. See Restriction note for further information.
  - Abrams, Radmila, 1972-1980; (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Badalic, Josip, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - Baker, Robert L., 1959-1972 (Box 6)
  - Beebe, John F., 1960-1972 (Box 6)
  - Beker, Miroslav, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Belinkov, Arkadij, 1968-1970 (Box 6)
  - Belyakova, Irina, 1978 (Box 6)
  - Ben, George, 1973-1978 (Box 6)
  - Benes, Hana, 1964-1978 (Box 6)
  - Besharov-Djaparidze, Justina, 1958-1971 (Box 6)
  - Blinoff, Marthe, 1962-1963 (Box 6)
  - Borovkoff, Anna, 1961-1974; 1986 (Box 6)
  - Brandunas, E., 1976; undated (Box 6)
  - Braun, Maximillian, 1963-1967 (Box 6)
  - Brown, Edward, 1965-1977 (Box 6)
  - Breschinsky, Zina, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Buehler, Gretchen, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Cetzverikova, Alexandra, 1959-1969 (Box 6)
  - Clark, Katernia, 1981-1987 (Box 6)
  - Daniels, Robert V., 1951-1954; undated (Box 6)
  - Davis, Alan, 1955-1956 (Box 6)
  - Drozdowski, Piotr, 1984-1994 (Box 6)
  - Edgerton, William B., 1967-2004; (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Fedulova, Margaret, 1959-1966 (Box 6)
  - Fiszman, Samuel, 1969-1998; 2000-2002; (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Friedberg, Maurice, 1965-1975 (Box 6)
  - Garrard, John G., 1968-1971 (Box 6)
  - Goscilo, Helena, 1986-1993 (Box 6)
  - Ginsburg, Michael, 1955-1967; undated (Box 6)
  - Gribble, Charles, 1968-1977 (Box 6)
  - Hammer, Louise, 1989-1997 (Box 6)
  - Hare, Richard, 1958-1966 (Box 6)
  - Harris, Jane Gray, 1973-1975 (Box 6)
  - Hartmann-flyer, Helene, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - Holub, Peter, 1955 (Box 6)
  - Ingham, Norman, 1963-1970 (Box 6)
  - Ivask, George, 1958-1971 (Box 6)
  - Jackson, Robert, 1960-1962 (Box 6)
  - Johnson, Marta, 1980-1995 (Box 6)
  - Johnston, Illinca, 1990-1991 (Box 6)
  - Kadic, Ante, 1959-1998; (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - Kagan-Kans, Eva, 1966-1997; (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Kasik, John Phillip, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - Katayev, Vladimir, 1978 (Box 6)
  - Kirk, Irene, 1962-1972; undated (Box 6)
  - Kusubova, Tatiana, 1966-1974; undated (Box 6)
  - Klagstad, Harold L., 1956-1967 (Box 6)
  - Lane, John Stanley, 1951 (Box 6)
  - Levin, Maurice, 1964-1971; undated (Box 6)
  - Lowe, David, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - Mankow, Polikorp, 1967-1972 (Box 6)
  - Martianov, Alexander, 1962-1982 (Box 6)
  - Matlow, Ralph, 1963-1967; undated (Box 6)
  - Milman, Nyusa (Box 6)
    - 1995-2002, (5 folders) (Box 6)
    - Outstanding Jr. Faculty Award (Box 6)
      - 1999, (2 folders) (Box 6)
      - 2000, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Newman, Laurence, 1967-1974; (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Oinas, Felix, 1958-2002; (3 of 6 folders) (Box 6)
  - Oinas, Felix, 1958-2002; (3 of 6 folders) (Box 6)
  - Vivian Parsons, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - Pope, Richard, 1969-1977 (Box 6)
  - Proffer, Carl, 1959-1974 (Box 6)
  - Radchenko, Feodor, 1968-1971 (Box 6)
  - Sangster, Rodney, 1964-1988; (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Scatton, Linda, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - Scherer-Virshi, 1959-1961 (Box 6)
  - Schultze, Sydney, 1974-1975 (Box 6)
  - Segel, Harold, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - Shallcross, Bozena, 1999-2001; (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Shaw, Joseph T., 1958-1970 (Box 6)
  - Shaw, Nonna, 1953-1962 (Box 6)
  - Skalenczenko, Tatiana, 1955-1979; (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Slamnig, Ivan, 1966-1968 (Box 6)
  - Slavatinsky, Lydia, 1963-1968 (Box 6)
  - Soudakoff, Mariamna, 1961-1962 (Box 6)
  - Sudakoff, Steve, 1970-1979 (Box 6)
  - Spieker, Sven, 1991-1995 (Box 6)
  - Stankiewicz, Edward, 1953-1966; undated; (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Strasheim, Lorraine, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  - Struve, Gleb, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Thompson, Ewa, 1967-1973 (Box 6)
  - Todd, Albert, 1965-1971 (Box 6)
  - Tucker, Eugenia, 1959 (Box 6)
  - Ushakov,Vladimir, 1959-1970 (Box 6)
  - Van Schooneveld, C.H., 1965-2003 (Box 6)
  - Varchaver, Andre, 1950-1953 (Box 6)
  - Vickery, Walter, 1953-1970 (Box 6)
  - Wasiolek, Edward, 1972-1974 (Box 6)
  - Whitman,Robert, 1962-1967 (Box 6)
  - Wierzewski, Wojciech, 1979-1982 (Box 6)
  - Yavener, Symond, 1959-1961 (Box 6)
  - Zalucki, Henryk, 1965-1969 (Box 6)
  - Zalucki, Maria, 1968-1989 (Box 6)
  - Zardetsky, Helen, 1967-1973 (Box 6)
  - Zawadowski, Leon, 1969-1973 (Box 6)
  - Zeldin, Boris, 1975-1977 (Box 6)
  - Zenkowsky, Serge, 1949-1963 (Box 6)